Guide to the Beekman Family Papers 1720-1920's MS 51
© 2011 New-York Historical Society
Beekman Family Papers
1720-1920's
MS 51
© 2011 New-York Historical Society
30.25 Linear feet (70 Boxes)
The collection contains material pertaining to multiple generations of the Beekman family, a prominent New York City family of Dutch ancestry. Between the eighteenth and the twentieth centuries, the Beekmans were intimately involved in the city's mercantile business, politics, and philanthropy.
Arrangement note
This collection has not been fully processed or arranged. It is loosely organized by family member, as reflected in the box and folder list. To further assist researchers, the quick-reference guide below is designed to group the boxes and folders chronologically as well as by Beekman head of family. When a folder or box is placed under a particular family member, it means the bulk of that material is from that time period. Note that the date ranges are approximate only.
Key: "Box #": "Folder #"
Ex: "1:2, 3, 4-5, 9" means Box 1, Folders 2, 3, 4 through 5, and 9
-------------------------
Henry Beekman (1688-1776): 1:12-13, 20(17th Century),
William Beekman- (1725-1795): 1:21-22, 11:1, 17(A), 17(B), 18, 19, 20, 21, 22, 23, 24(A), 24(B), 27:1, 3-4,6-11, 31(A):1, 31(B),
James Beekman (1757-1837): 4:2, 13(A), 13(B), 14(A), 14(B), 15(A), 15(B), 31(C), 32(A), 32(B), 34(A), 34(B),
William Beekman Jr. (1754-1808): 16(A), 16(B),
Gerard Beekman (1774-1833): 1:10, 11, 18, 19, 4:1, 3-5, 5(B):12, 6(B):13-17, 7(A)-Part 1:1-7, 8(B):10, 17-18, 11:2, 31(A):2-7,
Theophilus E. Beekman (bulk of doc from 1810’s-1820’s): 42
James W Beekman (1815-1877): 1:1-9, 14, 23-25, 2:1-10, 3:1-5, 5(A):1-9, 5(B):11(Part I-II), 13, 6(A):1-12, 6(B):18, 7(A)-Part I:8-12, 7(A)-Part II, 7(B):22-28, 8(A):1-9, 8(B):11-16,19, 9:1-7, 10:1-3, 11:3-10,12-13, 25(A), 25(B), 26(A)1-5, 27:2,5, 30(A), 30(B), 38(A), 38(B), 41(A), 41(B), 44:1-8,
Gerard Beekman (1842-1918): The bulk of the genealogical material is filed within these boxes and folders (James W. Beekman and future generations engaged heavily in family genealogy) 8(B):20, 12:1-8, 26(A):5-7, 26(B):8-9, 28(A), 28(B), 29, 38(B): 7 (Not much here but look at the end of the folder for genealogy), 39(A), 39(B), 40(A), 40(B), 43(A), 43(B), 44:9, 46,
Josephine L. Beekman, Recollections (1872-1953): 1:17,
Beekman Family: Typically children’s school papers, art, poetry, college admissions cards, and other documents that were filed separately from official or personal correspondence. 5(A): 10, 5(B): 14-17, 11:11, 33, 36 (Circa 1750-1800), 37 (Bulk 18th Cent), 44:10-12, 45,
OVERSIZED BOXES: 47
Access restrictions
Open to qualified researchers. Portions of the collection that have been microfilmed will be brought to the researcher in that format and can be made available by Interlibrary loan. Researchers on site may print out unlimited copies from microfilm reader-printer machines at per-exposure rates. See guidelines in Reading Room for details. Photocopying undertaken by staff only. Limited to twenty exposures of stable, unbound material per day. (Researchers may not accrue unused copy amounts from previous days.) Items that include presidential signatures will be presented to researchers in duplicate form.
Biographical/Historical note
The Beekmans were one of New York's most prominent families. Their name is perpetuated in New York City's Beekman, Ann, and William Streets, all named after family members, and in other namesake places throughout New York state.
The family first settled in the colony of New Netherlands in the mid-seventeenth century. Dr. William (Wilhelmus) Beekman (1623-1707), born in 1623 of protestant refugees Hendrick Beekman and Maria Baudartius, emigrated from the Netherlands to the colony in 1647 with Petrus Stuyvesant and served on the governor’s administration in multiple capacities. In 1652, William purchased Corleas Hook’s plantation on the Hudson river. A few years later he was appointed Vice Director of the Southern River (the Delaware River) territory in 1658, and for nine years was one of the burgomasters of New Amsterdam. In 1664, after he took an oath of allegiance to the English King Charles II, William was appointed sheriff of Esopus in Ulster County, where he served until 1672. During his service in 1670, he purchased an extensive property on Pearl Street along east river, extending west to present-day Beekman/William Streets and “The Beekman Swamp” west of that. In 1675, with the eruption of King Philip's War in New England, he and other prominent New Yorkers petitioned Governor Andros to dispose of their estates and move elsewhere in the colony. They were denied and imprisoned, but later released on bail. In 1683, he was named mayor and later purchased territory in Rhinebeck; he stayed on this property until his death in 1707. His son, Henry Beekman, was an Ulster County militia leader and, in return for his service, was provided with several large land grants in Dutchess County. Another son, Gerardus Beekman, served as temporary governor of the colony from 1709 to 1710.
Henry Beekman (1688-1776), the child of Henry Beekman and Johanna Lopers, was born in Ulster County in 1688. He married Janet Livingston in 1721, and after she passed away in 1724, remarried to the wealthy Gertrude Van Cortlandt in 1726. Henry, a prominent local landholder, was elected in 1724 to serve on the colonial assembly. He also completed a short-lived stint as New York County sheriff between 1732 and 1734. Henry retired from the assembly in 1758 and died at the family property in Rhinebeck in 1776.
William Beekman (1725-1795) was the son of Dr. William Beekman and Catherine De La Noy and brother of Cornelia Beekman Walton. A bachelor, Beekman managed the family real estate businesses and, on occasion, invested in mercantile ventures. During the summers, William resided with his bachelor brother Abraham at Rural Cove, one of the East River Beekman family estates.
Cornelia Beekman Walton (1708-1786), sister of James and William Beekman, married wealthy merchant William Walton on January 27, 1731, for which she had an eight hundred pound dowry from her father, Dr. William Beekman. Together they resided at the “Old Walton House” on Franklin Square in Manhattan. Cornelia’s financial accounts, particularly after the death of her husband in 1768, are very well represented within the collection and indicate her familiarity with business and trade.
James Beekman (1732-1807), brother of William Beekman, married Jane Keteltas, the daughter of a New York Dutch merchant family, on October 5, 1752. James began his lucrative career as a dry goods merchant in 1750, and his business boomed during the Seven Years’ War but suffered heavily during New York City’s occupation in the American Revolution. James, a patriot, during the war found his Mount Pleasant estate at Turtle Bay taken over by British commanders including Sir William Howe and Sir Henry Clinton and was forced to relocate his family to Kingston. In the post-Revolutionary era, Beekman and his family were active members in New York City’s high society and, after retiring to his Mount Pleasant estate in the early nineteenth century, he passed away on April 6, 1807. The mercantile papers of Beekman’s business are well represented within the collection.
Jane Keteltas Beekman (1734-1817) married James Beekman in 1752. Though records are incomplete, Beekman gave birth to between ten and twelve children; these included sons William, James, and Gerard, and daughters Mary, who married Stephen Bayard, and Jane, who married Stephen Van Cortlandt. Jane was largely responsible for coordinating the education of her many children and provided personal tutoring to the daughters prior to their formal instruction. Records within the collection—including an account book bearing her name—indicate that she was intimately involved in the family’s mercantile business and possessed a shrewd business acumen. Jane, a fixture of New York’s high society in the early national period and a frequent entertainer, split her time between Hanover Square in the fashionable business district and the family’s Mount Pleasant Estate.
William Beekman (1754-1808) was the eldest son of at least ten children born to James Beekman and Jane Keteltas. He graduated from Princeton in 1773, but continued to take classes well into 1775 and remained a bachelor throughout his life. William was bequeathed the family estate at Mount Pleasant upon the death of his father in 1807, but he passed away one year later and thus never retained possession of the property.
James Beekman, Jr. (1758-1837) was the son of James Beekman and Jane Keteltas. He attended Princeton at age ten but did not graduate, and so was instead educated by private tutors during the period of the imperial crisis. Not much information is available regarding his business or domestic affairs. James lived comfortably off of the proceeds of his deceased father’s estate and later inherited the Mount Pleasant property after his mother’s death in 1817. He married Lydia Watkins Drew and, after her death in 1833, became embroiled in a dispute over her estate with her executrix, Elizabeth Dunkin, that is well documented within the collection.
Gerard Beekman (1774-1833), son of James Beekman and Jane Keteltas, was the youngest child. Raised first in Kingston during British occupation and then in New York City, Gerard attended and graduated from Columbia College. An introspective and deeply religious man, Beekman led a quiet life as a bachelor until, at age thirty-six on April 9, 1810, he married Catherine Sanders, the daughter of a prominent upstate family. He and his wife only had one child survive to adulthood, James William. Beekman died of internal injuries in a stagecoach accident in 1833 and his wife would pass away two years later.
Theophilus Elsworth Beekman (1790-1858) was the son of Theophilus Beekman and Elizabeth Matthews. Beekman served as a Lieutenant in the United States Army during the War of 1812. He married Marietta (Maritta) Hathaway, whose father’s papers are contained within this collection.
James W. Beekman (1815-1877) was the only living child of Gerard Beekman and Catherine Sanders. He inherited his father’s considerable estate at Oyster Bay and Madison Avenue after Gerard’s death in 1833. A philanthropist and politician, James W. graduated from Columbia College in 1834. He would later attend Columbia Law School but, after graduation, elected not to practice. In 1840, he married Abian (Abby Anne) Steele Milledoler, daughter of the Reverend Philip Milledoler, President of Rutgers College. Together they had five children: Catherine B., Gerard, Philip, James William II, and Cornelia, of whom all but Philip would survive to adulthood. Beginning in his thirties, James W. was active in the administrative affairs of the New-York Historical Society, the Institution for the Deaf and Dumb, New York Society Library, Society for the Reformation of Juvenile Delinquents, the Woman’s Hospital, other antebellum benevolent organizations, and was a trustee at Columbia University. In 1848, he was nominated as a “Silver Gray” Whig candidate for the New York State Assembly. He held two terms in the New York State Senate where he grappled with issues relating to immigration, slavery, temperance, and the funding of public education. After retiring from politics following an intense political upheaval over the candidacy of Hamilton Fish to the United States Senate, he continued to devote his time to philanthropy and political issues. In 1861, James W. visited Washington with Thurlow Weed and Erastus Corning to attend the “Peace Convention.” His retirement pursuits included publishing on family history in the article “Founders of New York” in the book “Prominent Families of New York,” and he also published the book “Early European Colonies on the Delaware.” He died from pneumonia on June 15, 1877. His political, personal and institutional records are very well represented within the collection.
Abian “Abby” Steele Milledoler (1820-1897) was the daughter of Reverend Phillip Milledoler, a president of Rutgers College, and Margaret Steele Milledoler. She married James W. Beekman in 1840. She gave birth to four children: Gerard, James, Catherine, and Cornelia.
Gerard Beekman (1842-1918) was the son of James W. Beekman and Abian Milledoler. He, like Beekmans of previous generations, attended Columbia College and graduated in 1864. He received both Master of Arts and Bachelor of Law degrees in 1867, though he never actively practiced law. Instead, he served as a real estate manager for the many Beekman family estates he inherited at his father’s death. Gerard, like his father, was active in charitable and philanthropic ventures and, in 1910, he founded the Beekman Family Association and endowed the association on his death. He was very active in pursuing Beekman family genealogical material during his lifetime, and much of the genealogy within this collection was compiled by him at the turn of the twentieth century. ​
Sources:
Aitken, William Benford. Distinguished Families in America. New York and London: The Knickerbocker Press, 1912.
Burrows, Edwin G., and Mike Wallace. Gotham: A History of New York City to 1898. New York: Oxford University Press, 1999.
Lamb, Martha J., and Burton Harrison. History of the City of New York: Its Origin, Rise, and Progress. 3 vols, New York: A.S. Barnes, 1877.
Mann, Bruce H. Republic of Debtors: Bankruptcy in the Age of American Independence. Cambridge, MA: Harvard University Press, 2002.
New York (State). Legislature. Senate. "Documents of the Senate of the State of New York." Albany: Printed by E. Croswell, 1831.
Scoville, Joseph Alfred. The Old Merchants of New York City. New York,: Carleton, 1863.
White, Philip L. “Beekman, Henry”; http://www.anb.org/articles/01/01-01210.html; American National Biography Online, February 2000.
White, Philip L. Gerard G. Beekman, and James Beekman. The Beekman Mercantile Papers, 1746-1799. 3 vols New York: New-York Historical Society, 1956.
White, Philip L. The Beekmans of New York in Politics and Commerce, 1647-1877. New York: New-York Historical Society under a grant from the Beekman Family Association, 1956.
White, Philip L. Beekmantown, New York: Forest Frontier to Farm Community. Austin: University of Texas Press, 1979.​
Scope and Contents note
The Beekman Family Papers consist largely of correspondence (mostly in English, some in French and Dutch), business papers, legal papers, financial documents, real estate documents and court records. Many of these papers center around the business and political affairs of the family in New York City and their various landholdings and accounts in New York State.
This collection was organized by Philip L. White during a fellowship before 1950. He was a doctoral student in history at Columbia when he set to work gathering the information that served to comprise his biography on the Beekman family, entitled "The Beekmans of New York," an entry in the American National Biography for Henry Beekman, and the three-volume published collection of business papers in the "Beekman Mercantile Papers." Along the way, he compiled more than four hundred pages of notes which provides an interesting--albeit somewhat limited--summary of this collection. It also seems apparent that the last few boxes, numbered 40-47, arrived after his fellowship ended and thus remain unaccounted for in the summary. There is one oversized box in this collection, Box 47. A PDF-version of White's summary description is available here (note that it may take a few minutes to download).
In addition to the manuscript collection, White also consulted the bound volumes of the Beekman family collection in his work on the mercantile papers. Housed separately from the Beekman Family Papers, the bound volumes can be found online at the N-YHS library catalogue by searching for "BV Beekman." Each set of volumes listed online has a brief description and a date range that accurately describes its contents.
The "Arrangement" section below represents the most recent attempt to reorganize the collection in a more user-friendly way: chronologically. As the researcher will notice, White's notes and the "Container List" are not always accurate, nor do they represent the entirety of this collection. This online finding aid--constructed predominantly as a box and folder list--aims to fill those gaps and create a functional point of entry into this collection.
More detailed information about the contents of the collection is provided in the box and folder descriptions.
Provenance
Permanent loan from the Beekman Family Association.
Beekman, Henry, 1688-1776; Clinton, George, 1739-1812; Livingston, Peter R., 1766-1847; New York (State). Court of Chancery.; New-York Historical Society; Reformed Protestant Dutch Church (U.S.); Roosevelt, Theodore, 1858-1919; Union Club (New York, N.Y.); Union College (Schenectady, N.Y.); Van Cortlandt family; Walton Family; Account books; Accounts; Bills; Bonds (legal records); Business cards; Business papers; Churches--New York (State)--New York; Contracts; Correspondence; Deeds; Education - New York (City) - 19th century; Food -- United States; Indentures; Legal correspondence; Legal files; Legislators--New York (State); Letters (correspondence); London, England; Manhattan (New York, N.Y.); Maps; Personal correspondence; Photographs; Real property - New York (State) - New York; Real property -- New Jersey; Receipts; Slavery -- New York (State); Temperance -- New York (State); Union College (Schenectady, N.Y.); United States -- Religion -- 19th century.; Wills
- Box 1, Beekman Family, Correspondence, Legal Documents, Diaries, 1650-1940 (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  For additional detail, see White's guide, Volume 1, Pages 1-2, and Volume 2, Pages 426-438. White's descriptions are not organized by folder.
  - Mr. and Mrs. James W. Beekman, Correspondence from Children in Switzerland, Letters from Catherine Beekman while at Mrs Haines School, School Copybooks, Report Cards, 1850-1870 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - James W. Beekman, Correspondence from John N. Beekman, William F. Beekman, Eight Letters from Mrs. James W. Beekman to Friends, 1855-1875 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Material regarding James and John B. is missing from White's guide.
  - Mr. and Mrs. James W. Beekman, Correspondence from Son Gerard, 1855-1875 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Letters pertain primarily to Gerard Beekman's study abroud, and are in both English and French.
  - James W. Beekman, Correspondence from Rev. Maunsell Van Rensselaer and Mrs. Betsy Van Rensselaer, 1855- 1868 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Mr. and Mrs. James W. Beekman, Correspondence to and from William S. Milledoler, 1850-1860 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Mr. and Mrs. James W. Beekman, Correspondence from Captain and Mrs J.H. Graham and Cornelia Graham, 1854-1861 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Mr. and Mrs. James W. Beekman, Correspondence from Mr. and Mrs. Jacob G. Sanders, John Sanders, and James B. Sanders, 1855-1867 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Mr. and Mrs. James W. Beekman, Correspondence from Mrs. William Axtell Depeyster and J. Watts Depeyster, 1854-1868 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Mr. and Mrs. James W. Beekman, Correspondence from Rev. and Mrs. P. Martin Brett and Cornelia Brett; also, correspondence from Cornelia Brett to Catherine Beekman, 1854-1858 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Gerard Beekman, Correspondence (includes 1709 letter from Queen Ann regarding land grants in Imperial NY), 1709, 1810-1831 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence to and from B., Catherine, Deborah, or Elizabeth Beekman, 1779-1840 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Henry Beekman, 1711-1741, Correspondence and Legal Documents (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Henry Beekman, 1742-1745, Correspondence (bulk from Gilbert Livingston) (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Henry R. and James W. Beekman, Correspondence, 1850-1886 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Henry Beekman, 1746-1753 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Johannis Jr., Jacob, James J. Johannis, John C., John K., John, John James, John Jacob Beekman; Correspondence, Accounts, Agreements, Land Surveys, 1736-1835 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Josephine L. Beekman, Recollections, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Margaret, Maria, Peter Q., Sally, Verdine, William, and Samuel Beekman; Correspondence, Agreements, Estate Papers, 1768-1850 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Magnus Beekman, Listing for the Corporation, 1801 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - William Beekman, Dutch Documents (formerly in uncatalogued R.R. Livingston collection), 1652-1669 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - William Gerard Beekman, Legal Documents, Undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Patent Blueprint for Wawayanda, Undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Deed from Mary Elizabeth G. Beekman and Others to John G. Beekman, Trustee of Mary Depeyster, 1847 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - James Beekman Diaries, 1851, 1852, 1853, 1851-1853 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - James Beekman Diaries, 1861, 1866, 1867 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Box 2, James W. Beekman, Correspondence, Circa 1850-1870 (Box 2)
  For more information, see White's Guide, Volume 1, pages 2-23, which contains item-level detail' however, many folders are organized alphabetically and thus do not line up to the container list directly.
  - James W. Beekman, Correspondence Received, 1870's (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Includes institutional documentation for the Historical Society of Pennsylvania, the N-YHS, and the Metropolitan Museum of Art.
  - James W. Beekman, Series of Letters to Dr. William B. Casey, Senator James Dixon, Rev. Charles M. Jameson, Edward S. Rand, Baron Roenne, Dr. John K. Sappington, William P. Wainwright, 1854-1864 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - James W. Beekman, Correspondence Received (Alphabetical by sender last name), 1860-1864 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - James W. Beekman, Correspondence Received, 1857-1858 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - James W. Beekman, Correspondence Received, 1859 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - James W. Beekman, Matias Romero Letters, 1864-1868 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - James W. Beekman, Correspondence Received, 1854 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - James W. Beekman, Correspondence Received, 1855 (Box 2, Folder 8A)
  - James W. Beekman, Correspondence Received, 1856 (Box 2, Folder 8B)
    Not all material in this folder is listed in White's notes.
  - James W. Beekman, Correspondence Received, 1847, 1851-1852 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - James W. Beekman, Correspondence Received from Bryant Clay, Colfax, Grant, Mitchell, Scott, Sherman, Steele (includes bound letterbooks and loose letters), 1851-1867 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Box 3, James W. Beekman, Miscellaneous, Circa 1790's, 1820's - 1870 (Box 3)
  See White's guide: Volume 1, pages 24-27.
  - James W. Beekman, Notes, Clippings (regarding institutions and organizations), 1826-1886 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - James W. Beekman, 3 school reports, 24 bills and receipts, Europe 1854, 1 Summons to Chancery Court 1859, 1828-1859 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Gerard Beekman (1774-1833), Surveys and Accounts for 14 Leroy Place, 1828 and Manhattan Co Account Book, 1827-1832 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - James W. Beekman, Accounts and Receipts (Bulk 1850-68), 1796-1868 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - James W. Beekman, Notes of the Committee on a Village of Cottage Hospitals, undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Box 4, James Beekman, Gerard Beekman, 1790's - 1841 (Box 4)
  For more information, see White's guide: Vol 1, pages 28-39.
  - Record of Correspondence between James Beekman, Jr. (d. 1836) and Mrs. Elizabeth Dunkin (executrix) regarding Disposition of Estate of Beekman's Wife Lydia (d 1837), 1830-1836 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    White's notes do not describe all the material within this folder.
  - Bill of Sale for Negro Slave in 1753 (Slave owned by Catherine Beekman), Checkbook for the Manhattan Company, 1834-1835, Correspondence of Gerard Beekman 1798, Samuel Beekman 1778, Misc. Accounts, 1753-1835 (Box 4, Folder 2)